<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two letters touching the Trinity and Incarnation the first urging the belief of the Athanasian Creed, the second, an answer thereto.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1592</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12242154</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12242154</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56811</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64025)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56811)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two letters touching the Trinity and Incarnation the first urging the belief of the Athanasian Creed, the second, an answer thereto.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Athanasian Creed.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56811:1"/>
            <head>Two Letters touching the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The Firſt urging the Belief of the Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſian Creed. The Second, an Anſwer thereto.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>The Firſt LETTER.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Loving Couſin;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT'S no ſmall Trouble to me to hear you are fallen into the <hi>horrid</hi> Hereſy of the Socinians and Arians, <hi>viz.</hi> to deny the Holy Trinity and Incarnation of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: For you commend a printed Sheet, that is diſperſed under the Title of <hi>Brief Notes on the Creed of St.</hi> Athanaſius, and are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the Damnation which is there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt all ſuch as do not firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Doctrines contained therein, which have been always and are at this Day held to be the <hi>Great Fundamentals of Chriſtianity.</hi> And I take them to be ſo clearly revealed in Holy Scripture, that no Man well acquainted with Scripture, (as you are) can disbelieve them, without ſome <hi>Wantonneſs and Pride of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, a great Conceit and Confidence of their own Knowledg, and ſuch unpardonable Immodeſty, as admits of no Excuſe: And though ſuch Perſons may be otherwiſe pious and uſeful Men, yet there's no Reaſon why they ſhould not be damned as well as devout and vertuous Jews and Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I always took you for a <hi>modeſt Man,</hi> and one that had a great Reverence for what is revealed in Holy Scripture. But if you now <hi>reſolve never to allow that to be the Senſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, however plain and evident the Words are, which is not agreable to your Reaſon, but will put another Senſe upon them, though never ſo forc'd and violent,</hi> as in this Controverſy you do; I can no longer account you modeſt, but that you now betray the Pride and Conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which before lay hid, and that if you perſiſt in the Denial of the ſupream Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Son of God and of the Holy Ghoſt, you are to be rejected of all good Chriſtians as an Heretick, <hi>one that is ſubverted, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, being condemned of himſelf.</hi> For that it is not conſiſtent with any Man, but him that has long indulged in himſelf that Arrogance and Singularity which ſtops his Ears to ſober Truth, and ſhuts out of his Heart the Fear and Awe of God, or at leaſt never ſets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſeriouſly before the Divine Tribunal in the Conſideration of theſe Matters (as I am perſwaded befals ſome heady and hot Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trovertiſts) to ſhut his Eyes againſt <hi>the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Light</hi> of theſe <hi>neceſſary</hi> Doctrines, the Foundation of Chriſtian Religion as it is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. For <hi>the Myſtery of the Trinity runs through it, and gives it all the Strokes of Life and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as it is a poſitive Religion different from natural. I beſeech you therefore, Couſin, retire your ſelf into your own Heart, and ſet our Lord Jeſus upon his Throne before your Eyes, and conſider what you will anſwer to him, whom you have denied to be your God, and ſay he is but a made Lord, and that as a Mediator he is not God-Man, but Man only; and concerning the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56811:2"/>in whoſe Name you are baptized as well as in the Father and the Son, you yet deny him to be another Divine and Almighty Perſon. Conſider, I pray, that <hi>the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is not a ſpeculative Point, but that the whole Frame of Chriſtianity is built upon it, and that it is neceſſary to ſupport both our Chriſtian Worſhip, and our Chriſtian Hope and Comfort.</hi> Conſider alſo that all Hereſies are <hi>Works of the Fleſh,</hi> which notwithſtanding many great Biſhops, and ſome great Councils have been guilty of, even in this Point denying of three equal Perſons in God: And we know, that for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has maintained the groſs Hereſies of Tranſubſtantiation, and Idolatrous Worſhip of the Hoſt, with many other Superſtitions; all which ſhew that our corrupted Wills and Paſſions are as inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Hereſy and Superſtition as to other Vices and Immoralities. <hi>Faith is a Chriſtian Vertue, and a Man ſhall be puniſhed for the Faults of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding as well as any others. We muſt be as careful then to bring our Reaſon to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is divinely inſpired, as our Will to whatever is divinely commanded.</hi> I beſeech you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore again and again, examine your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſeriouſly, and the Holy Scripture ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely. Do not impoſe upon your ſelf to your own Deſtruction, by uncouth, nice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible and trifling Diſtinctions, for God will not be mocked. Sincerity is neceſſary to every good Chriſtian, and they that want it ſhall have their Portion with Hypocrites and Sinners. As you hearken to this altogether neceſſary Advice, you ſhall have me,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Condoling, or Congratulating Kinſman.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>The ANSWER.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Couſin;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS I was meditating on the little or no care Chriſtians take of their own Salvation, that unhappy Careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs afforded me the true Reaſon of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo little concerned for the Salvation of their Neighbours: I am glad to hear you are not of that Number, and I don't queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but you will be pleaſed that I am none of them neither, and that following your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, I deſire your Salvation with as much Earneſtneſs as you do mine. Moſt of thoſe whom the Church has ſet up for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Souls, are much more earneſt to get Preferments, and defend the Party wherein they are ingaged, by ſubtil Diſputes and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſecutions, than ſincerely to examine the Doctrines which they teach, and feed their Flocks with thoſe pure and ſolid Truths, which free from Sin and Error: Nor do they think that thereby they become accountable before God's Tribunal for all the Wandrings of their Diſciples. And laſtly, that both the blind Guide, and the Blind whom he guides, ſhall fall into the Ditch. Do but ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from their Study whatever is profane, and belongs not to the Character of a Paſtor, and the Treaſure of their Minds will ſoon be exhauſted; therefore imitate them not in ſuch a Diſorder. For my part, though I am a <hi>Lay-man,</hi> I think I am bound earneſtly to exhort my Brethren, and you particularly, to reſtore the Principle of our Reformation, which is almoſt degenerated into Popery; and to make uſe of <hi>our own Light,</hi> that we may be able to keep the Way ſet before us in the Scripture: This is the Proteſtants Right, we are in Poſſeſſion thereof, and we muſt not ſuffer our ſelves to be deprived of it.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you, dear Couſin, in the Name of God, to conſider, that when we were firſt delivered from the Roman Tyranny, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56811:2"/>againſt the abſurd Doctrines, that were impoſed upon our Faith, we cried down the Word of Men, and recommended only the Word of God, <hi>the Bible, the Bible, the Bible</hi> only, ſays <hi>Chillingworth.</hi> But we no ſooner got out of our former Slavery, by the help of ſo clear a Light; but we are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into a new one by a moſt unequal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. The Queſtion is no more concerning the pure Word of God; it is, ſay they, too equivocal and uncertain, and it is no hard Matter for Hereticks to make it agree with their particular Opinions. What then? we hear of nothing but Fathers, Tradition, Councils, Creeds, and new-coined Words, on purpoſe to keep Chriſtians within the Bounds of the Faith of their Anceſtors; Metaphyſical Terms, whereof Men have no fixed Notion, and yet they ſtop the Mouths of Hereticks, by making the Church ſpeak more clearly and reaſonably than the Holy Ghoſt did. But this is not all; ſome of the ſame Men who inveighed ſo much againſt the Inquiſition and Popiſh Violences, ſet up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves a Holy Inquiſition, and will hear of no Toleration, but oppreſs the Liberty of the Chriſtians, who dare ſpeak out their Mind, ſo far are they from ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing on Writings and a publick Profeſſion. One would think that by our many Diſputes with the Roman Church, concerning Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, we have acquired the Priviledg there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Give me leave therefore, dear Couſin, ſince you call me to God's Tribunal, to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon you to the ſame. Pray tell me, Ought we not to fear that God ſhould require from us the Truth of the Holy Scripture, with which we have been intruſted; that Light which we have put under a Buſhel, and his gracious Talent, which we have buried? If he asks, from whence we took thoſe <hi>proſane Novelties of a Science falſly ſo called,</hi> I mean that moſt ſtrange and barbarous Language in his Church, <hi>O Holy, Bleſſed and Glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, three Perſons and one God, have Mercy upon us;</hi> What ſhall we anſwer him? What if he ſhall oblige us to give an Account of our Faith of that monſtrous Creed of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> with which we honour our great Holy Days, and which you mention as the moſt illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Monument of the Faith of our Fathers. Where is the Scribe, where is the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher of this World, that can anſwer him to one of thoſe many nonſenſical Articles? How came ye, will he ſay, to find in my Word <hi>one Eſſence and three Perſons, rather than one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and three Eſſences?</hi> By what Partiality have you diſcovered a Figure in theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and have found none in theſe, <hi>The Word was God?</hi> Why did you diſtinguiſh two Natures in the Chriſt, whom I ſent you, whilſt you refuſed to admit of two ſorts of <hi>Being</hi> in the Sacramental Body, which he gave you? You were afraid of thoſe Words, <hi>To eat the Fleſh, and drink the Blood of the Son of God;</hi> and you had no Repugnancy for the literal Senſe of theſe, <hi>A Virgin brought forth God; The Jews crucified God?</hi> He can ask a thouſand ſuch Queſtions, to which we ſhall be able to give no reaſonable Anſwer, by reaſon of the Inequality of the Reverence we pretend to pay to his Word, and of our Unſteadineſs in the Uſe we make of our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Senſes.</p>
               <p>In Effect, I would fain have our Teachers to tell us by what Principle of Philoſophy, by what Rule of Language, that Concluſion is irght and neceſſary, <hi>viz.</hi> the Father is a Divine Perſon, the Son is a Divine Perſon, the Holy Ghoſt is a Divine Perſon; <hi>Therefore there are three Divine Perſons:</hi> and this ſhould not likewiſe be ſo; The Father is God, the Son is God, the Holy Ghoſt is God; <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are three Gods?</hi> Doth not common Reaſon tell us, that thoſe two Concluſions are like this? <hi>Gabriel, Raphael,</hi> and <hi>Michael,</hi> are three Angelical Perſons; <hi>therefore they are three Angels?</hi> The ſame might be ſaid of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who are both three hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Perſons, and three Men. This Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of natural Reaſon ought to prevail, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we are taught by the Scripture, that three Divine Perſons are not the ſame with three Gods, or that a God is three Perſons, and three Perſons a God. But where doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56811:3"/>it tell us ſo? What Texts can they alledg that are clearer to prove that Myſtery, than thoſe alledged by the Papiſts are, to prove their ſuppoſed Myſtery of one Chriſt and many Bodies, and of many Bodies and one Chriſt? How is it that with reſpect to the Sacrament, we are helped by our Senſes to put a reaſonable Senſe upon the Scripture; but with reſpect to the Trinity, Reaſon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes us ſo far, as to aſcribe to Scripture an abſurd Senſe, and contrary to its Simplicity? Is the Light of a ſenſible Man more certain than that of an underſtanding and reaſonable Man? Have we a greater Certainty, that a Piece of Bread is not a humane Body, than that two and one make three? Is the Myſtery of Chriſt's Sacramental Body more ſuitable to our Apprehenſion, than the Myſtery of his real and natural Body? How come we to know that there is ſomething that is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible in that Man, whom we ſee born and dead, and that there is no ſuch thing in the Bread which we take and eat? A God is joined to that, ſay ye, and why not to this? But we ſee ſtill ſome Bread, will ye reply. It is true, your Senſes do not deceive you: But have not the Apoſtles too ſeen with their Eyes, and touched with their Hands, the Man, who is called the Word of Life? and their Senſes have not deceived them. This is true, who can, doubt of it? How ſhall we come off? Shall we fly to another Nature hypoſtatically united to this, which is the Object of our Senſes? But then the Hereticks, who err about the Sacrament, may have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the ſame Shift, to avoid the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Senſes. Some will ſay that the Senſes can judg only of the Species which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the Sacrament; Some, that there is an inviſible Object in the Bread, which is the glorious Body of Chriſt; Some that there is an hypoſtatical Union of that Bread with the eternal Word, which raiſes the Myſtery ſo much above our Reaſon, that it loſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Right and Liberty of judging thereof, and lies under the Neceſſity of ſubmitting to the Authority of the Revelation, which is clear upon this Point; for it ſays, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> Now if our Reaſon is raſh in the Judgment it bears concerning the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, notwithſtanding the Evidence of the lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Senſe of the Scripture, which is on her ſide, what Raſhneſs will it not be to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her Judgment in the Myſteries of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation and Tranſubſtantiation, againſt the expreſs Revelation of God's Word, <hi>This is my Body?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will only ask you one Queſtion upon this Matter, and I deſire you to anſwer me in the Fear of God, and the Sincerity of your Heart. Why do you think you may with Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> ſay, that the Terms of <hi>Perſon, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, Begotten,</hi> &amp;c. are metaphorical, whilſt you cannot endure that thoſe you call Hereticks ſhould uſe the ſame Right, and according to Reaſon and Scripture, pretend likewiſe that the Title of <hi>God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to Chriſt, is alſo a metaphorical Expreſſion? Can any thing be more unjuſt? Furthermore, why do you take the Liberty to explain the Words of the Euchariſt thus, <hi>This Bread is the Repreſentation and the Figure of my Body?</hi> And why do you deny me at the ſame time the ſame Liberty, when I explain the Words in the Beginning of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel by theſe, <hi>And the Word was the Image of God?</hi> Your Injuſtice is ſo much the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, becauſe I may ground my Interpretation upon other Expreſſions of the Scripture, wherein Chriſt is formally called the Image of God, and becauſe you have no expreſs Texts of the ſame Scripture wherein the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Bread is called the Figure of Chriſt's Body. Now neither in my Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor in yours, the Image cannot be the Original. As the Bread hath but a Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Qualities with Chriſt's Body, not the ſame Qualities, and the ſame Subſtance: Thus Chriſt, as he is the Image of God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have the ſame Qualities nor the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with God: He only hath the Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divine Subſtance, which God hath communicated to him, by honouring him with his Unction, bearing Teſtimony to him, and crowning him with Glory as a Reward of his Sufferings: <hi>Becauſe he humbled himſelf to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56811:3"/>the Death of the Croſs, therefore the Father hath highly exalted him, and hath given him a Name which is above every Name.</hi> Now if Chriſt hath been dignified with that high Name, by reaſon of his Obedience and Vertue, it follows from thence, that he had it not by the Priviledg of his eternal Generation: For if ſo, the pompous Deſcription of Chriſt's Elevation ſet down in the Goſpel would be but a Shew and mere Pageantry.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dear Couſin, if you find in thoſe clear Texts of the Scripture the true Reaſon of Chriſt's being called God; believe me, do not fetch any other from the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Notions of the Athanaſian Creed, wherein neither you nor I can apprehend any thing, except we apprehend nothing. Notwithſtanding you are ſo bold as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt me a Sentence of Damnation upon the Words of that doting Writer, (who was not <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) and even to damn all thoſe who will give no Credit to his Ravings, let them be never ſo pious and charitable. O ſtrange Prejudice of Men! As for me i'le make bold likewiſe to tell you, that how falſe and ill grounded ſoever the Aſſurance of Salvation may be, which that Author pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to thoſe that believe his Viſions, it is yet more falſe, that thoſe good Chriſtians who refuſe to believe them, ſhall be damned. For there is nothing more certain and clear in the Goſpel than this, <hi>viz.</hi> That all honeſt and pious Men ſhall be ſaved, and that all thoſe who ſhall be ſaved, will be ſaved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out believing the curious Myſteries of the pretended <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Do but peruſe all the Evangelical Promiſes, and look if you can find any one that promiſes Salvation to thoſe who believe <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Trinity, and the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> I can ſhew you a thouſand which make Salvation ſure to Piety, or to a Faith inconſiſtent with the Faith of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> What Guide ſhall we then follow, this <hi>Creed</hi> which ſays, That <hi>whoſoever will be ſaved, ought to believe three Divine Perſons, and one Divine Eſſence,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who aſſures us, that <hi>eternal Life conſiſts in acknowledging his Father the only true God, and himſelf Chriſt Jeſus to be he whom the Father hath ſent,</hi> that is to ſay, the Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as? What Creed ſhall we pitch upon to be the Badg of our Chriſtianity, either the new ones, which ſpeak of <hi>God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, as three equal Perſons,</hi> or the ancient Creed of the univerſal Church, commonly called the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, which only ſpeaks of <hi>God the Father, Jeſus Chriſt his Son, and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> without giving the Title of <hi>God</hi> to theſe two laſt? and which expreſly aſcribing to the Father the Attributes of the Godhead, of <hi>Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes only to the Son that which is only conſiſtent with a Man, and cannot be aſcribed to the ſupream God without Blaſphemy, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>he was conceived, born, died, was buried, and raiſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as it is not the Language of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, to ſay, God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt; ſo it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Stile of the Scripture, which never gives the Title of God to Chriſt, when it joins him with the Father, in thoſe Places wherein it ſets before us the Objects of our Knowledg and Worſhip, and makes, as it were, a kind of Form or Confeſſion of Faith. The Reaſon of it is this, Chriſt is God with Reſpect to the Empire which he hath received from God over the new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which he hath taken out of the Chaos of Sin, and governs by his Father's Power: But with Reſpect to God his Father, he is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Miniſter of his Will, his Meſſenger, and is at moſt called <hi>the Lord,</hi> which is a Term of Inferiority in the New Teſtament, to denote him whom the Father hath made his Lieutenant, who hath received his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire from another, and is to deliver it to him, that intruſted him with it; <hi>God,</hi> ſay the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles, <hi>having made him Lord and Chriſt.</hi> According to this Rule, which the Scripture exactly follows, it doth not only deny the Title of God to Chriſt in the Abridgments of Faith which it affords; but it is wont to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it only to the Father excluſively of the Son, ſaying expreſly, that <hi>the Father is the only true God,</hi> and <hi>the Son the only Lord,</hi> as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56811:4"/>often as it puts together thoſe two Objects of our Faith. And in this remarkable Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is that we are to look for the true Senſe of the Scripture about this Myſtery; not in thoſe other Places wherein it doth not affect the ſame Exactneſs. Here, dear Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, I intreat you again, if you are a true Lover of Truth, ſeriouſly to conſider thoſe Texts of the Goſpel upon which my Remark is grounded. <hi>This is Life eternal,</hi> ſays Chriſt to his Father, <hi>to know Thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent. But to us,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, There is but one God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of whom are all things; and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things; and we by him. One God,</hi> ſays the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>and one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and Men, the Man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> Where is the Trinitarian, who on ſuch an occaſion would not ſay, <hi>One God, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> yet there is no mention made of the Holy Ghoſt; and as for the Son he bears only the Title of <hi>ſent, Lord</hi> and <hi>Mediator,</hi> that of <hi>God</hi> being not at all beſtowed upon him in thoſe Places? Who is the Trinitarian that would not ſay on the laſt cited Place, <hi>One God, and one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Men, Chriſt God-man?</hi> But <hi>God-man</hi> is too barbarous an Expreſſion, and the Holy Ghoſt is too wiſe to make ſuch a Conjunction. Laſtly, who is the Trinitarian, who would call the Father, <hi>the only God, the only true God,</hi> to diſtinguiſh him from the Son, by oppoſing God to Man, the only God to the only Lord and Mediator, in a Word, the Father to the Son, and one Perſon to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother? Do they not pretend that the Father cannot be called the only true God, but by Oppoſition to the falſe Gods of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens? But the Holy Apoſtle doth not only oppoſe him to the Idols of the Pagans, as the true one to the falſe ones, but to the only Lord, whom Chriſtians worſhip; inaſmuch as God by Excellence, God by himſelf, is oppoſed to the inferior and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Gods, whom he hath made ſuch out of his Grace and Liberality, <hi>I ſaid, ye are Gods: But to us,</hi> ſays the Holy Apoſtle, to us Chriſtians, <hi>there is but one God the Father, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Two Objects of our Faith really diſtinguiſhed; the one by the Name of <hi>one only God,</hi> the other by the Title of <hi>one only Lord.</hi> From whence it follows, as I have already ſaid, that Chriſt indeed is God, or rather a God, if conſidered as the Head of all the new Creatures, which God hath ſubjected to his Empire; but when joined to the Father, this Title vaniſhes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and he bears only that of his Miniſter and Ambaſſador; ſo true it is, that before the true and ſupreme God, any other God beſides him muſt fall and diſappear.</p>
               <p>You accuſe me of wreſting the Scripture, yet you ſee how I have brought you to the Neceſſity of putting a hard Senſe upon it, if you will maintain your Hypotheſis. The Texts that I alledg to you are clear and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, and you cannot avoid the Strougth of them, but either by a Philoſophy altogether incomprehenſible, or by ſome groſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory Shifts, or by a pitiful Wrangling, or even by Impiety and Blaſphemies. The Number of ſuch Shifts is endleſs, and I ſhall be contented to bring an Inſtance about eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of thoſe, which I have juſt now inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated. When we alledg that Croud of Texts, which ſay, that God is <hi>one,</hi> you fly to that famous Diſtinction of <hi>one Eſſence and three Perſons, and three Perſons and one Eſſence.</hi> If at the ſame time we alledg thoſe primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Facts of the Goſpel, wherein we ſee a moſt exact Hiſtory, not of <hi>a God,</hi> but of <hi>a Man</hi> like unto us, who was born, died, and was raiſed; you anſwer with another Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>two Natures and one Perſon, and one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and two Natures.</hi> This is your <hi>incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Philoſophy,</hi> which will have <hi>one</hi> to be <hi>three times one,</hi> three times himſelf: and pretends that by Virtue of I know not what hypoſtatical Union, a Man is the ſupreme God, and the ſupreme God a Man; ſo that it may be ſaid, <hi>The moſt high God was born, the moſt high God died.</hi> O! Who ſhall raiſe him from the dead? Again when we ſhew that the Queſtion concerning Chriſt's Divinity was decided by himſelf before the Jews, who accuſed him that being a Man, he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56811:4"/>equal to God; when one ſhews you, I ſay, that Chriſt vindicates himſelf from Blaſphemy, by proteſting that he ſaid he was the Son of God, only in ſuch a Senſe as is approved by the Law, founding his Right, not upon an eternal Generation, but upon a Heavenly Commiſſion and Unction, juſt as the other Gods, whoſe Example he alledges, <hi>If thoſe are called Gods, to whom the Word of God came,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſay ye that I blaſpheme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſaid, I am the Son of God?</hi> When one ſets before you ſo clear a Deciſion, and at the ſame time ſo favourable to thoſe you call Hereticks, how do you make ſhift? You ſay that Chriſt ſpake only according to the Need of the Jews, that there was no Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for him to give them further Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Yet at the ſame time that you return this curious Anſwer, which ſuppoſes that it was enough for the Jews, that Chriſt ſhould teach them, that he was <hi>a God by Office,</hi> you make an Objection taken out of the ſame Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Chriſt, wherein you pretend that he told the Jews he was <hi>God by Nature,</hi> when he ſays, that <hi>he and the Father were one,</hi> which Words you inſiſt upon to prove the Unity of Nature. This I call your <hi>groſs and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory ſhifts.</hi> Again, when one cites the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Text of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, wherein Chriſt makes <hi>eternal Life to conſiſt in knowing the Father the only true God,</hi> &amp;c. What do you anſwer to ſo ſtrong an Objection? You put upon thoſe Words a moſt forced and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Senſe, and ſay that they ought to be tranſlated thus, <hi>This is Life eternal, to know that thou Father and Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt ſent, are the only true God.</hi> This I call your <hi>raſh and impertinent Wranglings.</hi> In effect you are ſo bold as to make uſe of this in your Diſputes, to make ſhift as well as you can. But none of your Orthodox Tranſlations durſt take the ſame Liberty, neither the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, nor the Engliſh, nor the French, nor the German, nor the Dutch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I am ſure that if you would undertake a new Tranſlation, you have ſtill Modeſty enough not to fly to ſo ſhameful an Extremity. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (for I ſhould never have done, were I willing to inſiſt upon every thing) when one ſhews you in the 13th Chapter of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> that Chriſt is not the moſt high God, ſince he was ignorant of the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (for God knows all things) <hi>of that Day,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>no Man knoweth it, not the Son, but the Father only.</hi> In anſwer to this unanſwerable Objection, you put into Chriſt's Mouth <hi>a Jeſuitical Equivocation,</hi> pretending his meaning was, that he knew it not <hi>as a Man,</hi> though he knew it well <hi>as God.</hi> This I call your <hi>Impiety and Blaſphemy.</hi> Methinks, dear Couſin, you ſhould bluſh to impute to Chriſt <hi>a mental Reſervation,</hi> which you ſo much deteſt in the Prieſts of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Read Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in his Sermon upon <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.16. <hi>pag.</hi> 31, 32. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Anſwer, ſays he, (ſpeaking of thoſe Prieſts Equivocations) is, <hi>That in Confeſſion the Prieſt doth not know as Man, but as God, and therefore when he is asked any thing as a Man, he may deny what he knows as God.</hi> But the Doctor ſhews the Folly and Abſurdity of this Anſwer, <q>Becauſe, ſays he, this doth not ſalve the Contradiction; for to ſay, <hi>he doth not know,</hi> is as much as to ſay, <hi>he doth not any way know it,</hi> which is falſe, if he doth know it <hi>in any Capacity,</hi> becauſe he knows it <hi>as a Prieſt,</hi> and as ſuch he is not God, but Man.</q> Give me leave there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to look upon the Words you put into the Mouth of Chriſt, who is Truth it ſelf, as an Impiety and a Folly. <hi>He doth not know it,</hi> ſignifies that <hi>he doth not any way know it,</hi> which is falſe, if he knows it <hi>in any Capacity.</hi> Furthermore, it is falſe, that he doth not know it <hi>as Man,</hi> ſince he knows it <hi>as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and as ſuch he is not only God, but <hi>God and Man,</hi> ſay you. This is a Pattern of your unnatural Explications. I paſs by a great many others, to be ſhort.</p>
               <p>For the ſame Reaſon, I will only under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to overthrow <hi>the two Foundations</hi> of your Myſteries; which being done, nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to build your Faith upon. The one is <hi>the eternal Generation,</hi> and the other <hi>the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> or the Union of the two Natures. To begin with the eternal Generation; it is no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56811:5"/>difficult thing to demonſtrate to you, that it hath no ground in the Scripture. For foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as Chriſt, as you ſay, is God only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Account of his being <hi>begotten</hi> of God, or being <hi>the Son of God,</hi> we have nothing to do but to conſult the ſame Scripture, to ſee upon what grounds the Title of <hi>Son of God</hi> beſtowed upon Chriſt is founded therein. And if among thoſe Reaſons alledged by it, that of an eternal Generation is not to be found, it will neceſſarily follow, that ſuch a Generation is the Invention of your Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. Let us paſs by, if you will, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Place, wherein the Angel grounds the Title of Son of God upon the miraculous Conception of our Saviour in the Womb of a Virgin by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt: <hi>The Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſays he to the Virgin, <hi>ſhall come upon thee, and the Power of the Higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee; therefore that holy thing that ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> Again, let us omit that remarkable Paſſage, wherein Chriſt derives his Title of Son of God from his Unction and Heavenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <hi>Say ye that I blaſpheme whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſanctified and ſent into the World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſaid, I am the Son of God?</hi> It ſeems to me impoſſible to find two Cauſes or two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Chriſt's being the Son of God, more clear and expreſs than theſe two; <hi>becauſe</hi> he was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt in the Womb of a Virgin, and <hi>becauſe</hi> the Father hath ſanctified him, and ſent him into the World. However I will not inſiſt upon them, to ſtay the longer upon thoſe, in which the Word <hi>to beget</hi> is expreſly ſet down. I know but three Texts belonging to this Subject: The firſt is in <hi>Acts</hi> 13.33. where it is ſaid, that God hath begotten his Son by raiſing him from the dead; <hi>God,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>hath fulfilled the Promiſe unto us, in that he hath raiſed up Jeſus again; as it is alſo written in the ſecond Pſalm, Thou art my Son, this Day have I begotten thee.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.5. where it is expreſly ſet down, that God hath begotten his Son, by making him his High-Prieſt: <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>glorified not himſelf to be made an High-Prieſt, but he that ſaid unto him, Thou art my Son, to Day have I begotten thee.</hi> The third is in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.5. where the ſame Apoſtle tells us, that God hath begotten his Son by exalting him above the Angels: <hi>For unto which of the Angels ſaid he at any time, Thou art my Son, this Day have I begotten thee?</hi> In all theſe Texts there is no other Generation mentioned, but what is grounded upon the high Glory, which God hath conferred upon his Meſſias, by raiſing him from the dead, and making him Lord and Chriſt. And this Generation is ſo far from being eternal, that it is expreſly ſaid, it was performed <hi>to day,</hi> viz. the Day of his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion. Your Teachers have been often challenged to produce one ſingle Text of Scripture, wherein the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Generation is expreſly contained, and is the true Ground of Chriſt's being called the Son of God. If there is any, you will do me a Kindneſs to let me know it. Till this be done, I ought to acknowledg no other Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, but what the Scripture teaches, in thoſe clear and expreſs Texts which I have cited. Hereupon I will acquaint you with an Obſervation, for which I am beholden to a learned Man, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is a vaſt Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the manner of the Father's ſpeaking of Chriſt's Divinity, and that of the Apoſtles. The firſt ſetch'd his Original from I know not what Generation, which was made in the Beginning of the World: it is almoſt the only Generation ſpoken of by them, and their Platonick Stile always runs that way. On the contrary, the laſt ſhew the Source of it in his miraculous Birth, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in his Reſurrection and Exaltation. Hence it is that though Chriſt never called himſelf God, whilſt he had but a Glimpſe of his future Glory; yet the Apoſtles made no Scruple to honour him with that glorious Title, when they ſaw him crowned with his higheſt Glory &amp; Honour. Now that Difference in treating of the ſame Doctrine, which is to be ſeen between the ſacred Writers and your Teachers, is a material one, and ought to convince you, that they had not both
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56811:5"/>the ſame Principles, as your Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends. This general Obſervation concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fathers, is ſufficient to make me refuſe their Teſtimony, and look upon them as no good Interpreters of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and unfaithful Guardians of Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>I come now to <hi>the Incarnation</hi> or the Union of two Natures. You muſt confeſs, dear Couſin, that if we can from any Place learn the Diſtinction of two Natures in Chriſt, it is undoubtedly from <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. where he is called <hi>the Son of</hi> David <hi>according to the Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>the Son of God according to the Spirit of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, by the Reſurrection from the Dead.</hi> Here is the Son of <hi>David</hi> and the Son of God, the Fleſh and the Spirit, or the Word. Yet this Text is ſo far from proving two Natures in Chriſt, ſuch as you underſtand, that it is the ſtrongeſt Argument that can be brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, to confute that fooliſh and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Diſtinction, and the cleareſt Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary we have, to explain the other Paſſages, which ſpeak of Chriſt as a Man and a God. To be convinced of the Truth of this Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you need only compare together the 23d, 28th and 29th Verſes of the 4th to the <hi>Galatians:</hi> The Apoſtle ſays, that <hi>Iſmael was born according to the Fleſh,</hi> or that he was the Son of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the Fleſh, that is, according to the ordinary Courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but that <hi>Iſaac was born according to the Spirit,</hi> or by a miraculous Birth, that is, he was not ſo much the Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as the Son and Heir of the Divine Promiſe. This is granted by all. Now according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Stile, it is plain that Chriſt is <hi>the Son of</hi> David <hi>according to the Fleſh,</hi> that is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his natural Birth, becauſe he was born of a Woman, and <hi>Son of God according to the Spirit,</hi> viz. according to his ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Birth, becauſe he was born of a Virgin by the Operation of the Holy Spirit, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was raiſed from the dead, according to the Spirit of Holineſs, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks: In which Senſe he is not ſo much the Son and Heir of <hi>David,</hi> as the Son and Heir of God, or the Son of that great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which God had made to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs. <hi>According to the Spirit,</hi> can therefore ſignify only <hi>by the Divine Power,</hi> by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Birth and Reſurrection: Which plainly ſhews that the Diſtinction of two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in the Senſe you take them, is a mere Fancy; becauſe the eternal Generation is not at all mentioned by the Apoſtle in his Oppoſition between the Son of <hi>David</hi> and the Son of God, the Fleſh and the Spirit, the Humanity and the Divinity of Chriſt; and becauſe, ſpeaking of thoſe two Natures, taken in a right Senſe, he ſays, that Chriſt did partake of this laſt, when he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the Son of God, not by an eternal Generation, but a Divine Sanctification, and the Virtue of his Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid, it doth plainly appear, dear Couſin, that thoſe are truly <hi>Hereticks,</hi> who forſake the Simplicity and Purity of the Scripture, to coin Myſteries unknown to that Divine Revelation: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, I ſay, as it is evident from the new Words that have been coined to expreſs them: Which ſo plainly argues their Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that any one that is but ſincere, muſt needs be no leſs prejudiced againſt the ſtrange Words of <hi>Conſubſtantiality</hi> and <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> than againſt the monſtrous Term of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> They have both the ſame Original, Growth and Scope, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, with reſpect to us, they muſt have the ſame Deſtiny, and be look'd upon by all good Chriſtians, as the Effects of humane Paſſions, and the diſmal Cauſes of our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. In this you do condemn your ſelves. For if you pretend to teach the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which are taught in the Scripture, why do not you uſe the ſame Words? Your new Terms do betray your Cauſe, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that according to the Character of an Heretick ſet down by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> you do act not only againſt your own Conſcience, but againſt the Deſign of the Holy Ghoſt: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you can never ſpeak differently from him, but you muſt perceive at the ſame time, that you think differently, and by changing his Words, alter his Notions too.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56811:6"/>It is an eaſy thing to change a Doctrine by the Help of a new Word, eſpecially when to this new Word another is added, and the Explication thereof extended as far as poſſible, as Councils commonly do, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pretence of clearing Truth to its higheſt degree of Evidence, do ſo far depart from its Simplicity, that they quite loſe the ſight of it: ſo that it may be ſaid, that after ſo many new Pieces have been borrowed and ſewed to that firſt Garment, it hath loſt its Form and Colour, and is no more the ſame Cloth. But leſt you ſhould ſay, that it is ſtill the ſame Doctrine, expreſſed ſeveral ways, I ſhall prove the contrary in few Words. Obſerve therefore, (dear Couſin) that when the Scripture or the Creed of the Apoſtles, (which is for the moſt part made up of ſcriptural Terms) ſets down any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Doctrine, it makes uſe of ſo plain and intelligible Terms, either proper or metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical, that they may be underſtood by all Men. None can be deceived by them, if he is ſincere: For Example, when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed ſays, that there is <hi>an Almighty God, Maker of Heaven and Earth;</hi> that that moſt high God hath <hi>a Son, who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, was born, died, was raiſed from the Dead,</hi> &amp;c. any one preſently appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends with the whole Catholick Church, what is an Almighty God, Creator of all things; and what is a Son of God, who is his only Son, becauſe none but he hath a Virgin for his Mother, and God for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; what it is to be born, to die, and to be raiſed from the dead, and ſuch other Terms, whereby the Doctrines of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are expreſſed. There is no Diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, becauſe all Chriſtians have the ſame Notions of them: ſo that the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks who rejected the Doctrines contained in them, were forced to reject thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wherein they were mentioned. But pray how dare you pretend that the Terms which you have contrived, were contrived to ſignify the ſame things, ſeeing they are not commonly uſed by Men, being all taken out of Philoſophy? Beſides, their Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is liable to ſo many Changes and Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that ſometimes they ſignify one thing, and ſometimes another. This is ſo true, that the very Men of that Age in which they were coined, could not agree about their natural Meaning, one Doctor taking the Word <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> for that we call <hi>a Perſon,</hi> and another for that which we call <hi>a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> one Council rejecting the Word <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial</hi> as favouring Hereſy, and the other looking upon it as a Word fit to confute it. What may be the Reaſon, that when the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſpeaks, his Words are ſo popular and ſo clear, that reaſonable Men cannot miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the meaning of them? How comes it to paſs, that there is no Diſpute among Men concerning theſe Words, <hi>Son of God, who was conceived of the Holy Ghoſt, was born, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c? But when Men ſpeak, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Son <hi>conſubſtantial with the Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, not made,</hi> &amp;c. ſome do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them at all, let them be never ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; ſome, though very teachable, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure ſuch a Language; and ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree about their meaning, though every one of them conſiders it with a good Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the Fear of God. You need but conſult your <hi>Divines</hi> hereupon; ſome by <hi>three Perſons</hi> underſtand <hi>three Relations;</hi> ſome, <hi>three Capacities;</hi> ſome, <hi>three Minds;</hi> ſome, <hi>three Somewhats;</hi> and ſome, <hi>three individual Natures,</hi> as <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> The Reaſon of that Difference is obvious and plain: The Holy Ghoſt ſets before us the Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion full of Wiſdom, and accommodated to our Knowledg, and he fixes popular Notions to his Terms: But Men join to their Words remote, abſtruſe and metaphyſical Ideas, and they put ſuch an unnatural Senſe upon the Word of God, that even when they uſe it, it is only to defend their fooliſh and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Fancies.</p>
               <p>Do not tell me that it was wiſely done by the Church, to coin thoſe new Words, that the Senſe of the Scripture might be fixed thereby, and the Liberty of Hereticks ſtop'd. So pitiful an Excuſe doth not juſtify your Raſhneſs, it only juſtifies the Innocence of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56811:6"/>the pretended Hereticks. For <hi>what could hinder thoſe Hereticks, whom you accuſe of wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture, to uſe the ſame Subtilty, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the eluding of thoſe new Terms, which you will have them to ſubſcribe to?</hi> They could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do it, by putting upon them ſuch a Senſe as would not be prejudicial to their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. However this very thing, <hi>viz.</hi> their refuſing to ſubmit to thoſe new Impoſitions, is an undeniable Argument of their Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and if they cannot be brought, though in order to the ſaving of their Lives and Eſtates, to put an unnatural Senſe upon Mens Words, which they deſpiſe; much leſs will they wreſt the Senſe of God's Word, to which they pay the greateſt Reverence. From whence it follows, dear Couſin, that you your ſelf are a Heretick: I am ſorry to tell you ſo, but you force me to it. I have yet ſomething more to ſay to you, give me leave to ſpeak it out; for I do impart my Thoughts to you not in Anger, but with a Deſire of making you more attentive to thoſe things, in which your Salvation is ſo much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I mean that you run the Danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of thoſe <hi>Antichriſts</hi> ſpoken of by St. <hi>John,</hi> when he ſays, that <hi>whoſoever doth not confeſs that Chriſt, who came in the Fleſh,</hi> (for thus it muſt be rendred) <hi>the ſame is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> For firſt, ſince Chriſt ſignifies <hi>Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> an Antichriſt is one that is an Enemy to the Lord Chriſt's Anointing. Now do not you deſtroy that Divine Unction, pretending that Chriſt is the Son of God by an eternal Generation, which makes him uncapable of Unction or Exaltation, and overthrows that Fundamental Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>God made him Lord and Chriſt?</hi> Secondly, ſince <hi>to come in the Fleſh,</hi> ſignifies to come not like a conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prince, but like a Man of Sorrows, do not you deſtroy <hi>his Fleſh</hi> and Sufferings, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on one hand, that he is <hi>the moſt high God,</hi> who can neither be born, nor die; and on the other affirming, that Chriſt hath not the proper <hi>Perſonality</hi> of a Man, but <hi>the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed</hi> Perſonality of the eternal Word? ſo that according to your Notions, the Holy Virgin did not bring forth a Man, but <hi>an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature;</hi> the Jews have not crucified a Man, but <hi>an Humanity.</hi> An humane Nature is but an <hi>Ens rationis,</hi> and a mere Fancy: an Humanity can neither be born, nor die, nor be raiſed; which overthrows the firſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Chriſtian Faith, and may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of mere <hi>Antichriſtianiſm.</hi> For my part, dear Couſin, I can boaſt, Thanks be to God, of a contrary Character, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>he that confeſſeth that Jeſus, who came in the Fleſh, is Chriſt, is born of God.</hi> For I do not believe him to be the moſt high God, who can neither be born, nor die; but I believe he is <hi>a Man like unto us in all things, Sin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, who died for our Sins, and was raiſed for our Juſtification.</hi> I confeſs at the ſame time, that <hi>Jeſus is Chriſt the Lord, to the Glory of God the Father, who hath highly exalted him, and given him Power, Might, Honour and Glory.</hi> I am amazed to ſee that inſtead of building your Faith upon the Rock of that ſolid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, you will by all means found it upon ſuch Doctrines as have no Influence upon Practice. What Advantage is it to your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to reckon <hi>three Almighty and three Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Ones,</hi> as Objects of Confidence and Worſhip? Is Infinity capable of more or leſs? Is one the richer for having ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, than one only infinite? But to believe the only all good, wiſe, juſt and Almighty God was pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf to us by his <hi>Meſſias,</hi> who is the Prophet that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his Will to us, the King who engages himſelf to fulfil his Promiſes, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and merciful High-Prieſt, who can be touched with the feeling of our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: This, I ſay, is the Notion of a moſt wiſe Religion, which contains a great many Doctrines, wherewith the Mind is enlightned, and the Heart moved, a firm Support to our Faith, a ſolid Foundation to our Hopes, and a thouſand Encouragements to Holineſs of Life. I exhort you, dear Couſin, to a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſideration of ſo ſimple, but ſo rich a Religion. Do it with an honeſt and ſincere Heart, and I hope by God's Grace, that ſo great a Light will ſcatter the Miſt that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounds you, and help you to overcome the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56811:7"/>Prejudices of a Party. For it is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed that they are on your ſide; and one that owes his Religion to his Birth and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ought always to miſtruſt them. You are already gone a great way, adopting St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Maxim, <hi>viz. That whatever Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Scripture ſeems to command a Crime, muſt needs be figurative.</hi> Go on and be ſure, that any Expreſſion of the Scripture, which ſeems to require the Belief of an Abſurdity and a Contradiction, muſt needs be figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. The Reaſon is the ſame, for if the Scripture cannot require of you any thing that is contrary to the natural Notions you have of Piety; for Example, to eat humane Fleſh; it can neither impoſe upon your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief any thing that is contrary to your natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ideas of Truth; as for Example, That a Man who dies is the living and immortal God. I leave it to your Conſideration, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending you to God, and the Word of his Grace. I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Dear Couſin,</salute>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Couſin;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AFter a ſecond Reading of your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I have obſerved ſome Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Writings of your Teachers, which you took the Pains to tranſcribe, and upon which you ſeem to rely much as upon good Authorities. I ſhall tell you, that ſeveral of your Teachers have over-ſtrained the Matter, and that a modeſt Man ought not to depend upon their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. Some others have been ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant in their Judgment concerning Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, that they have blown hot and cold with the ſame Mouth, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Circumſtances they have been in. However we need only, in oppoſition to them, to conſider the Teſtimony of ſome more wiſe and moderate Divines, whoſe Names are no leſs eminent and reſpected in the Church of God. Theſe are ſo far from damning devout Chriſtians that are in Error, that they will not damn devout and virtuous Jews and Heathens. Do but read <hi>the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Life, Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. wherein Dr. <hi>Scot</hi> tells you, that <hi>to live according to mere natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is all that God expects from thoſe to whom Chriſtianity hath never been propoſed:</hi> and as for thoſe to whom it hath been ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he lays upon them no other Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but thoſe wherewith Chriſt hath ſtrengthned natural Religion. <q>Since Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, ſays he, hath improved the Duties of natural Religion upon new Principles, and inforced them with new Obligations; to render our Piety and Vertue ſtrictly and properly Chriſtian, it is neceſſary that we ſhould receive thoſe new Principles, and act according to thoſe new Obligations.</q> But leſt you ſhould diſpute about thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Obligations, which the Goſpel adds to natural Religion; I ſhall abridg this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute by a fine Place taken out of <hi>the Deſign of Chriſtianity:</hi> The pious Author of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Book ſays, (<hi>p.</hi> 236.) that if one would be ſure that one keeps the Foundation of Chriſtianity, and is in no damnable Error, he muſt examine himſelf thus: <q>Am I ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly willing to obey my Creator and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in all things commanded by them? Do I entertain and harbour no Luſt in my Breaſt? Do I heartily indeavour to have a right Underſtanding of the Holy Scriptures, and chiefly of the Goſpel, and to know what Doctrines are delivered there, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the bettering of my Soul by them, and the Direction of my Life and Actions according to them? If we can anſwer thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56811:7"/>Queſtions in the Affirmative, <hi>(who can doubt but all pious Hereticks may do it)</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Miſtakes we may labour under, they can be none of them ſuch as will undo our Souls, becauſe we ſhall have Cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from thence, that the Deſign of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is in ſome meaſure effected in us: And whatſoever Tenets may be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied and conſiſt with the true Love of God, and a ſollicitous Care to keep a Conſcience void of Offence towards him and Men, we may be certain that they belong not to the Catalogue of fundamental Errors. This obedient Temper is the moſt infallible Mark of an <hi>Orthodox</hi> Man; he that is endowed with it, though he may err, cannot be an <hi>Heretick.</hi>
                  </q> If I was as bold as you, dear Couſin, I would apply to you a fine Paſſage of our worthy <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury,</hi> in his Sermon upon <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42. wherein he blames the Raſhneſs of thoſe, who like you dare cenſure Error and Hereſy in others, whilſt they themſelves do not think <hi>of curing thoſe Luſts, Vices and Paſſions, which ſo viſibly reign in them.</hi> But I ſhall only cite that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reflection of his concerning thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Orthodox. <hi>Deluded People,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that do not conſider that the greateſt Hereſy in the World is a wicked Life; becauſe it is ſo directly and ſo fundamentally oppoſite to the whole Deſign of the Chriſtian Faith and Religion, and that God will ſooner forgive a Man an hundred Defects of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, than one Fault of his Will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to ſhew you in one Word, that when you attribute <hi>Immodeſty, Wantonneſs and Pride</hi> to Hereticks, you act againſt the Spirit of your Church; the Teſtimony of one of your Teachers only will ſuffice, ſince he ſpeaks for the whole Clergy: I mean the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>the Vindication of the conformed Clergy from the unjuſt Aſperſions of Hereſy:</hi> (That Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy was no leſs than <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> and <hi>Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi>) See how he vindicates your Teachers. <q>The Reaſon, ſays he, why they are accuſed of Hereſy, is their Moderation in Points of Controverſy. They do not confute their Opponent with a rude and infignificant Noiſe, nor think they ſhall ever convince him by hard Words and ill Names, which are the only Arguments that ſome Men are able to manage; but they conſider and are willing to make Allowances for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Infirmities of humane Underſtandings, and the ſtrong Prejudices of Education: and therefore they treat all Men gently, and are not rudely clamorous in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, but hope the beſt, and think as charitably as they can of thoſe that are of a different Perſwaſion.</q> See the Moderation of your Church, imitate ſo charitable and Chriſtian a Judgment, and ceaſe to damn, like Jews and Heathens, proud and conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, thoſe good Men, who work out their Salvation with Fear and Trembling, leſt with what Judgment ye judg, ye may be judged. The ſame Author will tell you, that the Term of <hi>Heretick</hi> is a Name that is given now-a-days liberally, and at a good rate, and that, <q>It is nothing but the Paſſion of the Opponents, that hath made that Name ſo very common as it is; for it is grown no more now than an ordinary Term of Reproach, for every angry Man, that would fain be dealing with controverſial Divinity, that it ſerves for one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Topicks for the great Profeſſors of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Scolding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Read but <hi>p.</hi> 70.</bibl>
                  </q> As to that <hi>great Conceit and Confidence of their own Knowledg,</hi> of which you think Hereticks are ſo full, that <hi>they reſolve never to allow that to be the Senſe of the Revelation, however plain and evident the Words are, which is not agreeable to their Reaſon, but will put another Senſe upon them, though never ſo ſorced and violent:</hi> As to this, I will tell you; Firſt, that they have borrowed that Method from the very Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Reformation. When, dear Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, thoſe Words of Chriſt are objected to you, <hi>This is my Body; My Fleſh is Meat indeed: My Blood is Drink indeed: Whoſo eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood,</hi> &amp;c. When, I ſay, thoſe Places of the Scripture are objected to you, who follow the Spirit of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Are you not reſolved never to allow that to be the Senſe of the Revelation, however plain and evident theſe Words are, which is not agreeable to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56811:8"/>your Senſes and Reaſon; and will you not put ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Senſe upon them, though never ſo forced and violent,</hi> as in effect you do, when you ſay that by <hi>the Body</hi> of Chriſt is meant <hi>the Figure of his Body; by eating his Fleſh, to believe in him,</hi> &amp;c? But I have already touched that Article in my Letter, and therefore I ſhall inſiſt no longer upon it. Secondly, Who puts upon the Scripture a more unnatural Senſe than you do in this Controverſy? Who hath a greater Pride of Underſtanding, and is more conceited of his Reaſonings? Hereticks ſo called, make Religion to conſiſt in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of a ſimple Faith, which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in the very Terms of Scripture, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſt the Form of ſound Words, ſo afraid they are to indulge their Reaſon too much, and to wreſt the Language and Intention of the Holy Ghoſt. But you on the contrary, who rely altogether upon humane Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, taken out of the Pagan Philoſophy, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſical Arguments and Abſtractions, or remote Conſequences; you, I ſay, muſt needs violate the ſacred Reverence due to God's Word, put a forced Senſe upon the Words of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhew at the ſame time a proud Confidence, by making the Scripture ſpeak any thing that agrees with your Notions. There is not <hi>one</hi> Word or Propoſition in that Scripture, but will ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy quite <hi>contrary things,</hi> according to your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions and Conſequences. You diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the Son of Man, and the Son of God, yet you confound thoſe two Terms, when you think fit, and make the Son of Man to be the Son of God, and the Son of God to be the Son of Man: If we ſay that it was the Son of Man that came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: you reply, that the Son of Man ſignifies there the Son of God. If we object that the Son of God knew not the Day of Judgment; you anſwer, that by the Son of God in that Place is meant the Son of Man: If one asks you, What's the Name of the firſt Perſon of the Trinity? you anſwer, <hi>the Father,</hi> and inſiſt earneſtly upon that Diſtinction of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to avoid the Force of this Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> That if Chriſt were the moſt high God, he would be the Father of himſelf. But if we object, that the Father only knows the Day of Judgment, and that he only is the true God and Creator of all things; then the Word <hi>Father</hi> ſignifies no more what it ſignified before, I mean the firſt Perſon of the Trinity, but the whole Trinity, and the very Son whom he hath begotten: ſo great is your Skill in doing and undoing the Work of the Holy Ghoſt, by contradicting Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in Seaſon and out of Seaſon. Let this ſuffice as to what concerns Words. The ſame may be ſaid of the Propoſitions of the Scripture, either affirmative or negative. By the enchanting Virtue of your Diſtinctions, the Affirmative becomes Negative, and the Negative Affirmative, when there is any need of it, and two contradictory Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are equally true and divine, if at any time it can ſerve your turn. It may be ſaid, that Chriſt hath wrought Miracles, and hath wrought no Miracles; that he knew not the Day of Judgment, and knew it; that he was born, and not born. In a word, one may overthrow the whole Goſpel and Creed, all thoſe Contradictions are Orthodox, if one doth but keep in his Mind the bleſſed Diſtinction of two Natures, which directs the Intention, and hinders a Man from tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Lie.</p>
               <p>By ſuch Tricks as theſe you pretend to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxy, and boaſt of a Principle that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes Holineſs and Piety; and, as you ſay, hath a great Influence upon all the Parts of Religion. But, dear Couſin, don't you know that the learned Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> who made a large practical Catechiſm, could find no Place in his Book for the great Spring of the Trinity? No queſtion but he look'd upon it as a thing altogether uſeleſs and uncapable of moving the Heart of Man. Make no doubt of it, it is a dry and empty Opinion, a Bone without Marrow or Meat, which can afford a Chriſtian Soul no ſort of good Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment in order to Piety. I confeſs there is a Trinity that hath Influence upon the Life of all true Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> that in which you and I have been baptized, the Father,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56811:8"/>the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt. But I muſt confeſs at the ſame time, that it is very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from yours, if underſtood according to Scripture. We have the Doctrine of the Father revealed by his Son, his Interpreter and Meſſias, and confirmed by the Gifts and Miracles of the Holy Spirit. This Doctrine hath ſo neceſſary an Influence upon the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Chriſtians, that without a right Knowledg of that Revelation we could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obey God's Commands, nor hope for his Rewards. And I confeſs, that with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to this primitive and capital Truth, any Man to whom that great Object is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, ſhall be no leſs accountable for the Faults of his Underſtanding than the Vices of his Will. There is a plain Reaſon for it, <hi>viz.</hi> that this Object doth not conſiſt in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Speculations, which the Simple cannot attain to, and the Ignorance whereof muſt needs be excuſable; but in plain and ſenſible Facts, for the believing of which, nothing elſe is required but the ſame Honeſty and Sincerity neceſſary to practiſe the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. For Example, We believe a Father, Creator of all things; a Son born, dead, raiſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and a Holy Ghoſt ſetting the Seal of his Miracles to that Revelation. Here is a Faith grounded upon undeniable Facts, which doth not require from us a ſeraphick Underſtanding, but ſome Honeſty to receive the Teſtimony of thoſe who relate them with as much Evidence as is neceſſary to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy an honeſt and reaſonable Mind. The Want of Faith or Underſtanding in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, is the Want of Probity and Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and therefore the Fault is inexcuſable. But if inſtead of ſo ſimple and ſenſible a Faith, you introduce your <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Faith of three Eternal, Almighty, and Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Ones, you make Unbelief of all things the moſt pardonable, nay, and the moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable too, becauſe ſuch a Faith is above the Reach of our Senſes, Reaſon, and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. So that we muſt read in the Goſpel, <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from Babes, and haſt revealed them unto the Wiſe and Prudent.</hi> I can aſſure you that not only many eminent Biſhops and great Councils have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Belief of ſuch a Myſtery, as you confeſs it, but that no good Chriſtian knew it, except perhaps in his Catechiſm, or a Book of Controverſy. How many Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Antiquity have we loſt, of which we could boaſt with great Reaſon? Who can tell but moſt Fathers had been on our ſide, if the Malice of their Enemies, the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of Monks, and the Flames of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors had not deſtroyed their Books? As for thoſe that remain, nothing but this can be concluded from them, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that prevailed (Hiſtory tells us by what means) took Poſſeſſion of Tradition and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxy. However we have ſtill in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creed the Primitive Truths, which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all Chriſtians, the ſaving Truths where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God's Providence fed the Faith of Chriſtians during the Quarrels of their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and the only Truths, for whoſe ſake true Martyrs have ſhed their Blood. I ſhall add, that the ſame Providence hath preſerved in all Sects and Ages a Body of Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, which makes the great and whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Goſpel. Let us conclude here, and ſeriouſly think, dear Couſin, that you and I ſhall be judged by Chriſt in the laſt Day only according to this Rule, independently on thoſe Opinions, which now a-days make the Subject of our Diſputes. I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56811:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
